{
  "reference_number": "11655",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The urgency of addressing climate disruption is acute right now. To get to no more than 1.5 degrees above preindustrial, net zero\n\n emissions by 2040 is currently advised by many scientists. The Government should set a flexible target based on the best science\n now but that that target can be made more stringent if new science or events dictate but not less stringent."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Option 3 is recommended because no decision now should in anyway risk handicapping the Climate Change Commission from giving\n its best advice or impede NZ from taking the steps necessary to achieve a 2050 zero limit,or better a 2040 limit."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "NZ should achieve its targets using domestic emissions reductions only; i.e., Option 1 but that any GHG transition plan incorporate as\n\n \"domestic emissions\" embodied carbon, both the aviation and shipping industries and the future of the tourism industry. Any form of\n international credit simply transfers our GHG liabilities to another state, which compromises their future capacity to manage their own\n\n resources or offset their own anthropogenic emissions. Also, relying on overseas efforts will deny NZers the major health benefits of\n reducing C emissions here--eg reducing emissions from changes in transport away from fossil fuels to active & public transport,\n reducing red meat and dairy from diets , increasing home insulation etc all have health co-benefits."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes-- but only in the case of a more stringent limit or shorter timeframe being identified as necessary by the Climate Commission and\n\n that recommendation receiving Parliamentary approval. New Zealand’s target must be primarily guided by the Paris Agreement and by\n any future international climate agreements signed by the Government."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But 6years to fit in with the election cycle I will also support"
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "The third budget should only be revised in exceptional circumstances on the recommendation of the Climate Commission and with\n the approval of Parliament-- not at the whim of an incoming government."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But once again, only on the recommendation of the Climate Commission and with the approval of Parliament-- not at the whim of an\nincoming government."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I support the Wise Response position on this question ie adding four new objectives, altering one and setting an order of priority as\nshown: i) (New) the need to preserve healthy ecosystem function for life supporting capacity, biodiversity and to provide ecosystem\n\nservices. ii) (New) the need for NZ to play its genuine and just part in the international effort to stabilise the climate and to maximise\nthe probability of successfully complying with the target limit for the wellbeing of future generations iii) (New) the need for precaution,\n\ngiven the level of uncertainty attached to estimates affecting the rate of GHG emissions and climate change iv) (New) the likelihood\nand the potential impact on climate change of any scarcity of material resources on the economy and GHG emissions, particularly that\n\nof fossil energy v) the three Government objectives for climate change policy: sustainable economy, global and local leadership and\ncreating a just and inclusive society vi) the Government’s obligations under the Treaty of Waitangi vii) social circumstances and, in\n\nparticular, the likely impact of the decision on fuel poverty viii) (altered) scientific knowledge about climate change and its limitations\nix) technology relevant to climate change x) energy policy and, in particular, the likely impact of the decision on energy supplies and\nthe carbon and energy intensity of the economy xi) fiscal circumstances and, in particular, the likely impact of the decision on\n\ntaxation, public spending and public borrowing xii) economic circumstances and, in particular, the likely impact of the decision on the\neconomy and the competitiveness of particular sectors of the economy 65. Rationale: The new clauses acknowledge the need for a\n\nclimate that sustains healthy ecosystems because our social and economic institutions depend on them. 66. The proposed order of\npriority seeks to reflect that relationship. The current economy is the least important consideration as it will need to adapt."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes--public scrutiny of the means by which the Government proposes to achieve the budget is the most powerful way in which the\npublic can be reassured that short-cuts are not being taken. I support a suitable timeframe be 6 months after an emission budget\n\nhas been set."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I recommend a highly precautionary budget that makes highest rates of emissions decline in the first years: it must not rely on overly\ncomplex technology or technical breakthroughs to achieve it. I want the Government to require the Climate Commission to include in\ntheir recommendations to Parliament clear process and timelines to make it straightforward to turn proposals into firm, funded policy\n\nand actions."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I support the advisory and monitoring functions proposed for the Climate Commission in the service of Parliament as follows:\nemissions budgets: advise on the most appropriate level and composition of emissions budgets and monitor our progress towards\n\nachieving these budgets  independent expert advice: provide independent advice on areas of the economy to focus on and\nachieve emissions budgets, and what is important to consider in getting there  2050 target: periodic check-in on the target level, in\n\nlight of changes in technology as well as accounting for what the rest of the world is doing. It could also advise the Government on\nthe most appropriate level for the 2050 target.  adaptation: monitor New Zealand’s progress towards addressing the risks posed by\nclimate change. Publish a report setting out progress towards delivering the national adaptation plan  international emissions\n\nreductions: advise on the extent to which international emissions reductions should be used towards our targets. 73. In addition I\npropose the Climate Commission: 1. proposes a national survey of New Zealand’s coasts so as managed adaptation plans can be\n\nrecommended to Parliament for coastal communities for sea level rise, inundation and storm surge. 2. monitors the collation of a\nnational inventory of anthropogenic emissions based on data provided by each local body."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I support a Fee and Dividend Scheme over an Emissions Trading Scheme. With a Fee and Dividend Scheme, I recommend the\nCommission advises Government, through Parliament, of the settings.I consider a weakness is that an ETS aims to limit climate\n\nchange indirectly by controlling emissions, rather than directly by limiting fossil fuel use. The indirect approach of the ETS undermines\nprecision and introduces uncertainty--it therefore offers more scope to ignore or subvert the scheme. I believe the ETS supports the\n\nwidely discredited neoliberal free-market and unfettered economic approach whichis a major cause of our exceeding the earth's\necological limits--only one problem of this failure to acknowledge our limits to growth is climate disruption."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, in the main. I want to see commissioners with expertise in -- Climate change policy with a major emphasis on the effects of\nclimate disruption on human health--suitably qualified health professionals will be required--eg from OraTaiao: the NZ Climate &\n\nHealth Council. Resource economics and impacts (including social impacts, labour markets and distribution); Te Tiriti o Waitangi, te\nreo me ona tikanga Māori and Māori interests; Climate and environmental science including mātauranga Māori; Experience with\n\naddressing adaptation challenges like planning, insurance and local government; Risk management; Engineering and/or\ninfrastructure Community engagement and communications."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The Zero Carbon Bill should be focused primarily on mitigation but adaptation and mitigation overlap. Therefore a separate work\nstream should include adaptation policy."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I supports the preparation of a national climate risk assessment, a national policy plan to address those risks identified, and a\nmonitoring and reporting framework. I also want a Risk Assessment for New Zealand be undertaken in parallel."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I strongly support setting up an adaptation reporting authority.This because climate warming with increased extremes, and sea level\n\nrise including storm surge and inundation is already affecting New Zealand communities and ecosystems. Monitoring and\ncoordinating a response to these risks is urgent.The strategies and regulations will occur through the RMA, LGA and LG Official\n\nInformation & Meetings Act, which need to be reviewed."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I strongly support the passing of this important bill. I congratulate the government for this initiative and the wide public consultation."
    }
  ]
}
